Guide to the J. Willard and Alice Sheets Marriott audio-visual collection 1960-1980
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
J. Willard and Alice Sheets Marriott audio-visual collection
1960-1980
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 801-581-8864 http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/
A0164
Marriott Corporation
Approximately 63 16mm films, 1 35mm film, 2 VHS videocassettes, 17 reel-to-reel audiotapes, 7 audiocassettes, 1 phonograph record, and 2 compact discs.
The J. Willard and Alice Sheets Marriott audio-visual collection (1960-1980) consists in large part of audio-visual materials produced or distributed by the Marriott Corporation. The bulk of the materials consist of production elements and final versions of various patriotic films sponsored by the Marriott Corporation, including "Honor America." Other materials include audio recordings of committees and stockholders meetings, audio and video tributes to Marriott and his company, and various other materials. J. Willard and Alice Sheets Marriott not only made a lasting impact in the service and hospitality industry but also left their mark in the political, religious, and academic arenas through their philanthropic works and activity in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
Biographical Note
John Willard Marriott (1900-1985) was born to Hyrum Willard Marriott and Ellen Morris at Marriott Settlement, Utah, September 17, 1900. He was the second of eight children and spent his early years helping with the family sheep ranching business. In 1918 he left for Connecticut and Vermont to serve a mission for the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
When he returned from his mission he attended Weber College from 1920 to 1922, and later enrolled at the University of Utah. In order to pay for his education, he worked during the summers selling woolen goods to lumberjacks in the Pacific Northwest. He graduated from the University of Utah in 1926, and spent the following year teaching English and working as treasurer of Weber College.
Mr. Marriott purchased the rights to sell Allen and Wright (A&W) root beer in Washington, D.C., and on May 20, 1927, he opened a root beer stand with Hugh Colton. A few weeks later he traveled back to Salt Lake City to marry Alice Sheets, June 9, 1927, in the Salt Lake Temple.
After the wedding, they returned immediately to Washington, D.C., and a few weeks later they opened their second shop. By winter they realized that they would need something other than cold drinks in order to keep the business running. However, it was prohibited to sell food in A&W franchises. The Marriotts received permission from Allen and Wright to add hot food to the menu. They decided to specialize in Mexican and Southwestern food, and the chef at the Mexican embassy graciously supplied them with a few recipes. Because the Marriotts were worried about the risk of losing their patronage if they closed the shop to make the changes needed for food service, they made preparations ahead of time so that it took only one night to convert the store. They finished just in time to open the next morning as The Hot Shoppe.
In 1928 Hugh Colton decided to sell his half of the business and return to Utah. The Marriotts purchased the other half of the business for $5,000.00 and they became sole owners of The Hot Shoppe.
The 1930s were a time of tremendous growth for the company and the Marriott family. The Marriotts' first child, J. Willard Marriott, Jr., was born in 1932. By 1934 the corporation had added drive-in restaurants with "running boys" that provided customers with in-car service. In addition, the Marriotts had pioneered the world's first in-flight airline catering service. In 1939 the Marriotts' second son, Richard Edwin Marriott, was born.
Much of the company's expansion efforts came to fruition in the 1940s and 1950s. The corporation built several new restaurants and opened numerous industrial, defense plant, and school cafeterias. A corporate recipe card system was developed and a test kitchen was built to standardize food preparation and portions. In 1957 the corporation expanded into the hotel industry with the first Marriott Motor Hotel in Arlington, Virginia.
The company continued to grow under Mr. Marriott's control until 1964, when he turned over the company presidency to his son, J. Willard Marriott, Jr. Mr. Marriott continued to be heavily involved with the corporation as chairman of the board.
However, corporate affairs did not wholly absorb Mr. Marriott's interest during these years. He was actively involved in religious, academic, political, and community organizations throughout his life.
He played an important part in the administration of the affairs of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints in Washington, D.C. In 1948 he was called to be president of the Washington Stake, a position he held until 1957, when he was appointed chairman of the General Chaplains Committee of the Mormon Church. He was actively involved with the Nauvoo Restoration Project and had a keen interest in the archaeology of the Book of Mormon. He also was instrumental in raising money for many building funds and served as an important liaison to church headquarters in Salt Lake City for the construction and dedication of the Washington, D.C. Temple.
The Marriotts retained close ties with academic institutions in Utah. In 1969 they made a substantial gift to the newly opened University of Utah Library which was subsequently named the Marriott Library. They later made another generous gift, this time to Brigham Young University, for the Marriott Activities Center which was dedicated in 1973. Mr. Marriott received honorary doctorate degrees from both institutions, as well as from Weber State College.
As a loyal Republican, Mr. Marriott formed close friendships in the national political arena. His list of friends included Dwight D. Eisenhower (a frequent customer of the Hot Shoppes), Richard Nixon, and Ronald Reagan. He was appointed by Nixon to chair both the 1969 and 1973 inaugural committees and served as chairman of the executive committee for Honor America Day for many years, along with committee members Billy Graham and Bob Hope. The Marriotts were life-long contributors to the Republican National Committee and supporters of George Romney and Richard Nixon's bids for the presidential nomination. Mr. Marriott also served on the board of governors for the United Service Organizations.
Mr. Marriott was always held in great esteem by his colleagues. He served as president of both the Washington Restaurant Association and the National Restaurant Association, and received numerous awards in the food and lodging industries. Throughout his life, he was affiliated with many business and civic organizations including the Burning Tree Club, the Indian Creek Country Club, Bald Peak Colony Club, Columbia Country Club, Capitol Hill Club, Federal City Council, the Washington Admirals, the National Association of Manufacturers, Riggs National Bank, the American Historical and Cultural Society, American Motors Corporation, Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Company, and the Acacia Mutual Life Insurance Company.
Mr. Marriott died of a heart attack on August 13, 1985, at his summer home in New Hampshire.
Alice Sheets Marriott was born October 19, 1907, in Salt Lake City, Utah to Alice Taylor and Edwin Spencer Sheets. She graduated with honors from the University of Utah in 1927 at age 19. She was a member of Phi Kappa Phi Honor Society and Chi Omega sorority.
Two days after graduation she married J. Willard Marriott in the Salt Lake Temple and moved to Washington, D.C. to help with the A&W root beer stand he had opened a few weeks before. Shortly after her arrival, they opened a second stand. Mrs. Marriott's early responsibilities included collecting accounts and taking receipts to the bank. Although the business was quite successful during the summer months, it was apparent that in the approaching winter months they would need more than root beer to keep the business afloat. Food service in the franchise was prohibited, but the Marriotts were able to secure special permission from Allen and Wright to add food to the menu.
The Marriotts discussed the idea of serving Mexican and Southwestern food, but neither had any experience in food preparation of this kind. Since Mrs. Marriott had majored in Spanish in college, she was able to talk to the chef at the Mexican embassy who provided her with a few recipes and the address of a Mexican food supply house in San Antonio, Texas.
Mrs. Marriott practiced cooking the recipes while Mr. Marriott made preparations to modify the stand for food service. They were determined to have everything ready in order to change the stand as quickly as possible, so they wouldn't lose their patronage. In the fall of 1927 the changes were made and the stand was transformed overnight. The Hot Shoppe was now in business, with Mrs. Marriott as the chef.
In 1930, Alice Taylor Sheets, Mrs. Marriott's mother, married Senator Reed Smoot and with that marriage came the Marriotts' inclusion in the political circles of Washington, D.C. In addition to these social activities, Mrs. Marriott continued to be very involved with the business, even after the birth of their sons, J. Willard Marriott, Jr. in 1932 and Richard Edwin Marriott in 1939. She was instrumental in key decision-making which affected the company's growth and success, and even helped design and decorate company restaurants and hotels and scouted out new locations for company expansion.
Mrs. Marriott's political activities were varied and extensive throughout her life. From 1955 to 1957 she served as assistant treasurer for the League of Republican Women for the District of Columbia, and in 1957 was appointed vice president of the organization, a post she held for two years. She continued to affiliate with the League of Republican Women, serving in numerous positions in subsequent years. In 1959 she was named to the District of Columbia Republican State Executive Committee. She was a member of the Republican National Committee from 1959 to 1976, and during those years she served as vice chairman and as an executive committee member. She served on the Arrangements Committee for the Republican National Conventions of 1960, 1964, 1968, and 1972, and was treasurer of the conventions in 1964, 1968, and 1972. She was vice chairman of the 1969 Inaugural Committee and honorary chairman of the 1973 Inaugural Committee.
In addition to her political responsibilities, Mrs. Marriott was actively involved with various organizations in the community, including the Goodwill Industries Guild, the Capital Speakers Club, the International Neighbors Club, the Arthritis and Rheumatism Association of Metropolitan Washington, and the National Advisory Committee for Children and Youth. She also helped found the Welcome to Washington International Club.
The nation's arts community has benefitted greatly from Mrs. Marriott's service and philanthropy. In 1971 she was appointed chairman of the Advisory Committee on the Arts for the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, and in 1972 was appointed to the board of trustees. She is now an honorary trustee, having served two 10-year terms on the board and executive and finance committees. She has also served on the board of directors of the National Ballet Society, and is a former member of the Women's Committee of the National Symphony Orchestra.
Mrs. Marriott's dedication to academic excellence has been manifest not only in her college years, but throughout her life. She holds two honorary Doctor of Humane Letters degrees, one from Mount Vernon College and one from the University of Utah. The University of Utah has been the recipient of the Marriott's support and generosity for many years. In 1989 the new dance building was dedicated as the Alice Sheets Marriott Center for Dance in recognition of her particular interest in the arts. In 1988 for the Marriott Library's twentieth anniversary, Mrs. Marriott made a sizeable donation, and in the tradition of the family, her son, J. Willard Marriott, Jr., chaired the university's capital campaign which far exceeded its goal of one hundred and fifty million dollars. At the conclusion of the campaign, the Marriott's made a significant donation to the library.
Mrs. Marriott's counsel and advice have been sought by various individuals and organizations throughout her life. She is a member of the American Newspaper Women's Association, the Capitol Hill Club, the Washington Club, the 1925 F Street Club, and has been named to the honorary board of the National Committee for Prevention of Child Abuse. She serves as a member of the National Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases Advisory Council and is on the board of directors of the Arthritis Foundation. She is also an active member of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
Prior to Mrs. Marriott's death on April 19, 2000, she served as director emeritus of Marriott International Incorporated and Host Marriott Corporation. She served one of the longest periods of active board service in American business history.
The J. Willard and Alice Sheets Marriott audio-visual collection (1960-1980) consists in large part of audio-visual materials produced or distributed by the Marriott Corporation. The bulk of the materials consist of production elements and final versions of various patriotic films sponsored by the Marriott Corporation, including "Honor America." Other materials include audio recordings of committees and stockholders meetings, audio and video tributes to Marriott and his company, and various other materials.
The films are arranged alphabetically according to topic.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the J. Willard and Alice Sheets Marriott papers (Ms 164) and photograph collection (P0164).
Patriotism; Hotels; Media and Communication; Sound Recordings; Moving Images; Sound recordings; Moving images
- Greer, Undated
  - Greer, misc., Undated; 16mm film (Reel 1)
  - Heads, tails, outs, can 3 Greer, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 2)
  - Tail Greer can 1, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 3)
- Honor America, 1976
  - Honor America, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 4)
  - Honor America 9/10/76, 1976 September 10; 16mm film (Reel 5)
  - "Honor America", "Battle Hymn" behind Indian Princess, "Honor America" color work print, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 6)
  - Honor America color work print, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 7)
  - Honor America (final version) 35mm, miscellaneous 35mm, Undated; 35mm film (Reel 8)
  - Honor America, Kennedy, America the beautiful, various cuts, trims, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 9)
  - Honor America MOS pre-program, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 10)
  - Honor America music, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 11)
  - Honor America Old radio part 2 (outs), no bells, Jack Armstrong (side 2), moon (outs), Undated; 16mm film (Reel 12)
  - Honor America, 1. Pre-Program, 2. Telly Savalas, Annette Funicello, O.J. Simpson, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 13)
  - Honor America reel 2, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 14)
  - Honor America reel 2 cam 1, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 15)
  - Honor America reel 2 cam 2, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 16)
  - Honor America reel 2 cam 3, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 17)
  - Honor America reel 3, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 18)
  - Honor America reel 3 cam 1, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 19)
  - Honor America reel 3 cam 2, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 20)
  - Honor America reel 3 cam 1, 2, Battle Hymn, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 21)
  - Honor America reel 3 cam 3, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 22)
  - Honor America r-2 A.M. pickups, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 23)
  - Honor America – Rock around the clock, the perfect combination, snuggled on your shoulder, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 24)
  - Honor America track 2 head, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 25)
  - UCIF Honor America, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 26)
  - UCIF Honor America FX-1, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 27)
- July 4th, Undated
  - July 4th head 5, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 28)
- Let Freedom Ring, Undated
  - Freedom revised, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 29)
  - Freedom track a, track b, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 30)
  - Let Freedom Ring Again (3 reels), Undated; 16mm film (Reel 31)
  - Let Freedom Ring Again a-roll, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 32)
  - Let Freedom Ring Again b-roll, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 33)
  - Let Freedom Ring, President Nixon, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 34)
  - Smaller related reels, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 35)
- Marriott: The Spirit of Success, Undated
  - Marriott: The Spirit of Success, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 36)
- Proudly They Came, Undated
  - Broadcast productions Proudly They Came short version narration, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 37)
  - Proudly They Came, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 38)
  - Proudly They Came short version, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 39)
  - Proudly They Came short version a and b 1 of 2, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 40)
  - Proudly They Came short version a and b 2 of 2, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 41)
  - Proudly They Came short version narration, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 42)
  - Proudly They Came track b, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 43)
  - Short version track a Proudly They Came, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 44)
- Misc, Undated
  - Amos and Andy, comp may track final version, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 45)
  - Balfour color rev composite a and b release print, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 46)
  - Battle Hymn, old narration, FUH AR, FUH APP, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 47)
  - Bob Hope trims, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 48)
  - Broadcast servicesa, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 49)
  - Bronson Gentry, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 50)
  - Dub units dialogue a and b 1, 2, 3 of 3, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 51)
  - Gordon Films for master, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 52)
  - Many misc. small reels, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 53)
  - Misc., Undated; 16mm film (Reel 54)
  - Misc., Undated; 16mm film (Reel 55)
  - Misc. trims, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 56)
  - Sound trims and outs narration/applause, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 57)
  - Sound trims and outs narration/applause, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 58)
  - Sync trims cameras 1 and 2, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 59)
  - Track A, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 60)
  - Unlabeled, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 61)
  - Van Sant Dugdale Baltimore, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 62)
  - Marriott amusement park advertisement, Undated; 16mm film (Reel 63)
  - Shots of Washington D.C., Undated; 16mm film (Reel 64)
- Marriott: The Spirit of Success, Undated
  - 50th Anniversary, Undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 65)
  - 50th Anniversary congratulations to Mr. and Mrs. J. Willard Marriott, 1977 May 21; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 66)
  - The 50th Anniversary greetings, Undated; Compact disc (Disc 67)
- American Marketing Association Award Ceremony, Undated
  - American Marketing Association award ceremony, Undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 68)
  - American marketing association, Undated; Compact disc (Disc 69)
- Honor America, Undated
  - Bob Hope "Honor America", 1970 June 4; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 70)
  - Bob Hope intro, Undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 71)
  - Eddie Walker why honor America?, 1974; Audiocassette (Cassette 72)
  - Pat Gates/Bob Hope voice of America, 1970 June 29; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 73)
  - Phone conversations with Bob Hope Committee for "Honor America Day", 1970 June 22; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 74)
  - Proudly they came to honor America, 1970 June 22; Phonograph record (Disc 75)
- Inaugural Committee, Undated
  - Inaugural Committee, Undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 76)
  - 1973 Inaugural Committee press office de-briefing, Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 77)
- Let Freedom Ring, Undated
  - Let Freedom Ring Again, 1977 April 20; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 78)
  - Narration: Son of LFRA 1 of 2, Undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 79)
  - Narration: Son of LFRA 2 of 2, Undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 80)
- Stockholder Meeting, 1975 November 18
  - Stockholder meeting 1 of 2, 1975 November 18; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 81)
  - Stockholder meeting 2 of 2, 1975 November 18; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 82)
- Misc., Undated
  - #1 My Youth, #2 Youth and Mission J. W. Marriott, Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 83)
  - #3 can't read J. W. Marriott, Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 84)
  - #7 memo begins 1/4 of the way through, Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 85)
  - Elderly woman, Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 86)
  - "The Financial Page" Bill Marriott 2 shows, Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 87)
  - Horatio Alger awards, 1974 May; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 88)
  - Marriott: The Spirit of Success, Undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 89)
  - Mormon Tabernacle Choir "God be with you until we meet again", Undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 90)
  - A most remarkable man, Undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 91)
  - Sen. Watkins 5/18, comments on article JWM "10 Angels for Christmas", Ladies Home Journal, (Large families on small income), 1954 November 8; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 92)
  - "The Spirit of '76", Undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 93)